How far would you go for a friend?
Free Willy is a family, adventure, drama film directed by Simon Wincer.
When maladjusted orphan Jesse vandalizes a theme park, he is placed with
foster parents and must work at the park to make amends.
There he meets Willy, a young Orca whale who has been separated from his family.
Sensing kinship, they form a bond and, with the help of kindly whale
trainer Rae Lindley, develop a routine of tricks.
However, greedy park owner Dial soon catches wind of the
duo and makes plans to profit from them.
Jesse, played by Jason James Richter.
Willy, played by Keiko.
Rae Lindley, played by Lori Petty.
Randolph Johnson, played by August Schellenberg.
Glen Greenwood, played by Michael Madsen.
Annie Greenwood, played by Jayne Atkinson.
Free Willy is a 1993 family drama film, directed by Simon Wincer, produced by Lauren Shuler Donner and Jennie Lew
Tugend, written by Keith Walker and Corey Blechman from a story by Walker and distributed by Warner Bros.
Pictures under their Family Entertainment imprint.
The film stars Jason James Richter in his film debut, Lori Petty, Jayne Atkinson, August
Schellenberg, and Michael Madsen with the eponymous character, Willy, played by Keiko.
The story is about a 12-year-old orphaned boy named Jesse who
befriends a captive orca, Willy, at an ailing amusement park.
When he discovers that the park owner has been planning to dispose of
Willy, he hatches a scheme to break Willy out of captivity.
Released on July 16, 1993, the film received positive attention from critics and was a
commercial success, grossing $153.7 million from a $20 million budget.
It grew into a small franchise, including an animated television series, two sequels, and a
direct-to-video reboot in addition to inspiring the rehabilitation and release of Keiko.
The film marked Keith Walker's only film as screenwriter, and
last project before his death on December 30, 1996.
The film explores themes of whale, social worker, freedom,
social work, human animal relationship.
The tone is emotional.